Register of the Alfreds Bilmanis Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Alfreds Bilmanis papers,
1919-1968
45003
Bilmanis, Alfreds, 1887-1948
8 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 1 oversize folder (4.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, speeches and writings, memoranda, reports, and printed matter, relating to Latvian foreign relations, conditions in Latvia during and after World War II, and postwar Latvian refugees and émigré affairs.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat to find the full extent of the collection.
Biographical Note
1887 Born, Riga, Latvia
1910 Graduated summa cum laude from Moscow University, with a degree in history
1919 Married Halina Salnicka in Tuczyn, Poland
1920 Chief of Press Section, Latvian Ministry for Foreign Affairs
1925 Received his Ph.D. in history from the University of Wilno (Vilnius)
1929 Visited and lectured in the United States
1930 Latvian delegate to the League of Nations
1932-1935 Latvian Envoy Extraordinary, Moscow, USSR
1935-1948 Latvian Envoy Extraordinary (ambassador) to the United States
1942 Author, Latvia and Her Baltic Neighbors, Washington, D.C.
1948 Died
1951 Posthumous publication of A History of Latvia, Princeton
Scope and Content Note
Acquired in 1948, with a significant increment coming to light in 2003, the Alfreds Bilmanis collection in the Hoover Institution Archives comprises documents relating to the career of one of the most important diplomats and historians of independent Latvia. As a scholar, Bilmanis published numerous articles and books on Latvian and Baltic history during his lifetime, but he received wider public recognition in his capacity as a diplomat occupying important and sensitive posts at a key time in his country's history.
Bilmanis's diplomatic career took him to Moscow in the 1930s, where he witnessed firsthand the effects of Stalinism, and then to the United States, where he served as Latvia's envoy during the tumultuous period before, during, and after World War II. When the Hitler-Stalin pact of 1939 assigned Latvia to a Soviet "sphere of influence," followed by the country's forcible annexation by the USSR in 1940, Bilmanis energetically protested, defending the cause of Baltic independence in Washington in his role as ambassador, and elsewhere, in his role of public speaker and historian.
Throughout the war, Bilmanis continued to publish articles, pamphlets, and books, all of which reflected an unwavering belief in Latvia's right to restored independence. While the actions of Germany and the Soviet Union meant that such a prospect was increasingly remote, Bilmanis nevertheless did achieve some tangible results as a diplomat. Latvian assets abroad were protected, as were certain gold reserves. Perhaps more importantly, in terms of the future status of Latvia, the United States never recognized the legality of the Soviet annexation of the Baltic States in 1940, nor did it do so when these states were re-annexed in the wake of the defeat of Nazi Germany. During this time, Bilmanis worked closely with the Latvian envoy to Great Britain, Kārlis Zarinš (Charles Zarine), and there are a number of letters from Zarinš in the CORRESPONDENCE series of the collection.
In keeping the cause of Baltic independence alive in the arena of public opinion, Bilmanis drew upon his skills as a writer and historian. He was later viewed by many within the Latvian diaspora and within Latvia itself as an important spokesman for Latvian national aspirations during a time when the country no longer existed as a legal entity. In 1968, on the twentieth anniversary of his death, Bilmanis was honored with the publication of a Festschrift consisting of articles written by a number of his colleagues and fellow historians.
The Bilmanis collection consists largely of correspondence and printed matter relating to Bilmanis's diplomatic activities in the United States. The correspondence, in particular, sheds light on the common struggle waged by Estonian, Latvian, and Lithuanian representatives as they sought to make the case for Baltic independence before the United States government and in the arena of public opinion.
Bilmanis was an early advocate of a commonwealth system for the three Baltic States, in which each would preserve its identity and independence within a federal structure. There are materials in the CORRESPONDENCE and SPEECHES AND WRITINGS series of the collection regarding this concept. Bilmanis wrote many letters to the editors of prominent American newspapers, and these are to be found in the SPEECHES AND WRITINGS series. His major historical work, A History of Latvia, was published posthumously, and is not part of the collection. The many writings produced by Bilmanis in his capacity as Latvian envoy to the United States are to be found in the SPEECHES AND WRITINGS part of the collection, as are reports and aide-mémoires for which Bilmanis was the primary author.
The LATVIAN LEGATION OFFICE FILE series includes materials produced by the Latvian Legation in Washington that were written by others or are unattributed. Some of these may have been authored by Bilmanis. The SUBJECT FILE contains copies of treaties concluded by all three Baltic States during their "first independence" between the two world wars. There is a good deal of information about each Baltic country in this file, as well as materials relating to the actions of Soviet and German occupying forces in the region before and after the Second World War. There are also materials concerning the resistance movement in Latvia conducted by the organization Latvijas Centrala Padome, whose representatives were based in Sweden, as well as information on the activities of the underground Latvian Social Democratic Workers Party during the same period.
The PRINTED MATTER series of the collection contains a number of émigré publications, as well as examples of newspapers produced by Latvians in displaced person camps in occupied Germany. There are also a number of publications in Lithuanian, Russian, and English.
The Bilmanis collection complements another collection in the Hoover Institution Archives, that of Jules Feldmans, who served as Bilmanis's successor as Latvian envoy to the United States, following Bilmanis's death in 1948. Bilmanis and Feldmans had worked together closely during the lifetime of the former, and there is a significant correlation between the two collections.
Throughout the register, Latvian spellings are given for Latvian names. Thus, Bilmanis's first name is Alfreds, rather than the name he used in the United States, Alfred. Where Latvian spellings differ significantly from their English counterparts, the English version is given in parentheses.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
World War, 1939-1945--Latvia.; Latvians in foreign countries.; Refugees.; World War, 1939-1945.; Latvia.; Latvia--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.; Soviet Union--Foreign relations--Latvia.; Latvia--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--Latvia.; Soviet Union.; United States--Foreign relations.
Occupations
Diplomats--Latvia.
Container List
- Biographical File, 1945-1968. (Box 1)
  Bibliography, concert program, credentials, and sheet music, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Bibliography. Sprudzs, Adolf, "Dr. Alfred Bilmanis' Writings," in Adolf Sprudzs and Armins Rusis, eds., Res Baltica, Leyden, Netherlands, 1968. (Folder 1: 1)
    Photocopy
  - Concert program, 1945 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Credentials. Photocopy of State Department accreditation of Bilmanis as Envoy Extraordinary, Minster Plenipotentiary, and Consul General of Latvia, 1947. (Folder 1: 3)
    Also includes photocopies of three supplemental pages detailing the continued recognition by the United States of its treaties with independent Latvia
  - Sheet music. Typescript copy of the Latvian national anthem, by Kārlis Baumanis, in English, n.d. (Folder 1: 4)
- Correspondence, 1940-1948. (Box 1)
  Letters, telegrams, and enclosures, largely relating to Bilmanis's diplomatic service in Washington, D.C., arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent. Includes copies of letters sent to Bilmanis which are neither addressed to him nor written by him
  - General, 1940-1947
    - A-M (Folder 1: 5)
    - N-Z (Folder 1: 6)
  - Unidentified, 1941-1947. (Folder 1: 7)
    Includes typescript draft of letter to Soviet ambassador(?), 1944
  - Acheson, Dean, 1944-1946 (Folder 1: 8)
  - American Red Cross, 1944-1945 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Baltic American Delegation (Constantine R. Jurgela), 1944., See also Lithuanian American Information Center (Folder 1: 10)
  - Berzinsh, A., 1945 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Brynes, James F., 1945-1946 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Budrys, Jonas, 1945 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Čamans, Joseph, 1945 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Carnegie Endowment for International Peace (Nicholas M. Butler, Malcolm W. Davis, James T. Shotwell), 1943 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Chicago Latvian Club (John Skudris), 1945 (Folder 1: 16)
  - Cicognani, A. G., 1941-1945 (Folder 1: 17)
  - Danzis, Gustav, 1944 (Folder 1: 18)
  - Ekis, L., 1943 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Encyclopedia Britannica (E. H. Powell), 1942 (Folder 1: 20)
  - Estonia. Saatkond voi esindus (United States), 1941-1946 (Folder 1: 21)
  - Feldmans, Jules, 1945-1946 (Folder 1: 22)
  - Graham, Malbone W., 1943 (Folder 1: 23)
  - Grew, Joseph C., 1945 (Folder 1: 24)
  - Grosvald, O., 1940-1945 (Folder 1: 25)
  - Gruszka, S., 1943 (Folder 1: 26)
  - Halifax, Viscount, 1942 (Folder 1: 27)
  - Hermanson, Richard, 1941-1945 (Folder 1: 28)
  - Hollyday, Worthington, 1943 (Folder 1: 29)
  - Hull, Cordell, 1941-1942 (Folder 1: 30)
  - Kaan, Herbert von, 1943 (Folder 1: 31)
  - Kalni"ņš, V., 1945 (Folder 1: 32)
  - Kraus, René, 1942 (Folder 1: 33)
  - Lasmanis, Kārlis, 1945 (Folder 1: 34)
  - Latvian Central Committee (Latviesu Centrala Komiteja), 1946 (Folder 1: 35)
  - Latvian Refugee Committee, 1945 (Folder 1: 36)
  - Law, John, 1945 (Folder 1: 37)
  - Lenow, John, 1943-1945 (Folder 1: 38)
  - Liepins, R., 1945 (Folder 1: 39)
  - Lithuania. Legacija (United States), 1941-1946 (Folder 1: 40)
  - Lithuanian American Information Center (Constantine R. Jurgela), 1945-1948 (Folder 1: 41)
  - Margolin, A., 1943 (Folder 1: 42)
  - Moon, Vika, 1943 (Folder 1: 43)
  - Nash, Walter, 1944 (Folder 1: 44)
  - Overseas News Agency (Jacob Landau), 1943 (Folder 1: 45)
  - Peterson, R. J., 1942-1945 (Folder 1: 46)
  - Pudsell, Frederick, 1945 (Folder 1: 47)
  - Schwager, Charles, 1943 (Folder 1: 48)
  - Senn, Alfred, 1942 (Folder 1: 49)
  - Sulzberger, Arthur Hays, 1942-1946. (Folder 1: 50)
    Includes correspondence relating to coverage of Latvia by The New York Times
  - Svensk-Lettiska Hjälpkommittén (Kārlis Lasmanis, Harry Wallin), 1945., See also correspondence with Kārlis Lasmanis (Folder 1: 51)
  - Thomsen, Hans, 1941. (Folder 1: 52)
    Relates to the declaration by Bilmanis of the existence of a state of war between Germany and Latvia, subsequent to the German invasion of the Soviet Union, and includes a copy of a supporting letter to Secretary of State Cordell Hull
  - Tilmanis, Arturs, 1945 (Folder 1: 53)
  - Valters, Miķelis, 1943-1945. (Folder 1: 54)
    Includes materials relating to displaced persons' camps in Germany
  - Vitols, Hugo, 1945 (Folder 1: 55)
  - Zalcmanis, Janis, 1945 (Folder 1: 56)
  - Zarinš, Kārlis (Charles Zarine), 1940-1946. (Folder 1: 57)
    Includes materials sent to, and prepared by, Zarinš in his capacity as head of the Latvian Legation in London
- Speeches and Writings, 1941-1948. (Box 2)
  Aide-mémoires, articles, book, letters to the editor, and reports, arranged chronologically by title
  - "Latvia and Other Baltic States Were Paying Propositions," n.d. (Folder 2: 1)
    Typescript
  - "The Latvians and Latvia," n.d. (Folder 2: 2)
  - Press statement on parliamentary elections in Latvia, 1940 July 13. (Folder 2: 3)
  - "Latvia: A Victim of Unprovoked Aggression by Soviet Russia," New York Times, 1940 July 23. (Folder 2: 4)
    Printed copy
  - Statement made to Secretary of State, Washington, D.C., 1941 June 25. (Folder 2: 5)
  - "Swastikas on the Latvian Airplanes," letter to the editor, PM, 1941 August 12. (Folder 2: 6)
  - Latvia and Her Baltic Neighbors: Three Stars between the Anvil and Hammer, Washington, D.C., 1942. (Folder 2: 7)
  - Aide-mémoire, 1942 February 24. (Folder 2: 8)
  - "Latvians are Not 'Bolshevik Brothers'," letter to the editor, Evening Star, 1942 May 3. (Folder 2: 9)
    Typescript text and cover letter
  - "Latvians Declared Never Hostile to Jews," New York World-Telegram, 1942 June 9. (Folder 2: 10)
    Typescripts of telegram and Bilmanis's text, and printed copy of article to which he was responding
  - "General-Directorate Imposed on Latvia by Nazi-Germans – Illegal, Null and Void and Violates Sovereign Rights of Latvia," 1942 July 28. (Folder 2: 11)
    Printed copy of press statement
  - Press statement, 1942 November 13. (Folder 2: 12)
  - The Baltic States and the Freedom of the Baltic Sea, Washington, D.C., 1943. (Folder 2: 13)
  - "Baltic States' Second Occupation during this War," in Latvia under German Occupation, Washington, D.C., 1943. (Folder 2: 14)
  - Letter to the editor, Evening and Sunday Star, 1943 January 10. (Folder 2: 15)
    Typescript of Bilmanis's text, and printed copy of article to which he was responding
  - Letter to the editor, Christian Science Monitor, 1943 February 23. (Folder 2: 16)
  - Letter to the editor, PM, 1943 March 3. (Folder 2: 17)
    Typescript letter and reply from John P. Lewis
  - Letter to the editor, Life, 1943 April 10. (Folder 2: 18)
    Printed copy and typescript copy of additional letter by the Polish ambassador, Jan Ciechanowski
  - Speech, Polish Constitution Day, Washington Irving High School, New York City, 1943 May 2. (Folder 2: 19)
  - Letter to the editor, Christian Science Monitor, 1943 October 26. (Folder 2: 20)
  - Letter to the editor, Washington Post, 1943 October 29. (Folder 2: 21)
    Typescript and printed copy
  - Letter to the editor, New York Post, 1943 November 19. (Folder 2: 22)
  - "The Foreign Policy of Russia," speech, 1944 March 21. (Folder 2: 23)
  - "Latvian Minister Says His People Want Atlantic Charter Freedom," Evening Star, 1944 October 17. (Folder 2: 24)
  - "Baltic States Stand Firm," New York Herald Tribune, 1945 January 28. (Folder 2: 25)
  - "Latvian History," Washington Post, 1945 March 11. (Folder 2: 26)
  - Latvia as an Independent State, Washington, D.C., 1947. (Folder 2: 27)
    Printed copy of review by Edgars Andersons in Sauksme, no. 11/12, 1947. Folder contains entire serial issue
  - Latvia: Country and People, Washington, D.C., 1948. (Folder 2: 28)
- Latvian Legation Office File, 1934-1946. (Box 3)
  Aide-mémoires, lists, and memoranda and reports, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Aide-mémoires, 1941-1944. (Folder 3: 1)
    Includes materials pertaining to the Latvian Legations in Washington and London, and whose authorship is uncertain. Typescripts
  - Lists, 1934-1946
    - Latvian place names, 1934 (Folder 3: 2)
    - Latvian refugees and missing persons, 1940-1946. (Folder 3: 3)
      Includes names of Latvians in Brazil, Canada, China, and the United States
    - Latvian officials deported into the Soviet gulag, 1941 (Folder 3: 4)
    - Latvian diplomats abroad, 1946 (Folder 3: 5)
  - Memoranda and reports, 1935-1944
    - General, 1943 (Folder 3: 6)
    - About Latvia and the Baltic states
      - General, 1935-1944. (Folder 3: 7-8)
        Unattributed writings; may include some authored by Alfreds Bilmanis
      - Written by L. Elkis for the Latvian Legation, Washington, D.C.
        - Latvia: Economic Resources and Capacities, Washington, D.C., 1942. (Folder 3: 9)
        - "Russian Bolshevistic Atrocities in Latvia," 1943 April. (Folder 3: 10)
- Subject File, 1920-1948. (Box 3-4)
  Clippings, correspondence, pamphlets, reports, and serial issues, arranged alphabetically by subject
  - Baltic States--Politics and government, 1940-1945., See separate headings for each country for more materials regarding individual histories. (Folder 3: 11)
    Includes photocopy of secret instructions, in Russian, to Soviet security agents regarding the arrest of "anti-Soviet elements" in Lithuania, Latvia, and Estonia
  - Estonia--Politics and government, 1940-1991 (Folder 3: 12)
  - Latvia
    - Economic conditions, 1945 (Folder 3: 13)
    - Foreign relations
      - Soviet Union, 1929-1944 (Folder 3: 14)
      - United States, 1928 (Folder 3: 15)
  - Latvian Red Cross, 1945 (Folder 3: 16)
  - Latvian Social Democratic Workers Party, 1944 (Folder 3: 17)
  - Latvijas Centrala Padome (Latvian Central Council), 1944-1945. (Folder 3: 18)
    Materials pertaining to underground resistance in Latvia during World War II, and to the activities of this organization, based in Sweden
  - League of Nations, 1920-1939. (Box-folder 4: 1)
    Copies of published proceedings concerning the three Baltic States, and copies of various international treaties to which they were signatories, as recorded by the League of Nations
  - Lithuania--Politics and government, 1940-1991. (Folder 4: 2)
    Includes copies of instructions to Soviet security forces, in Lithuanian and in English translation, regarding the handling of "anti-Soviet elements" in Lithuania
  - Merchant ships--Latvia, 1942. (Folder 4: 3)
    Includes materials relating to the sinking of Latvian cargo ships during World War II, and to postwar litigation concerning the Soviet nationalization of the Latvian Shipping Company
  - Refugees
    - Germany (West), 1945-1948. (Folder 4: 4)
      Materials relating to refugees from the three Baltic States, primarily those from Latvia, living in displaced person camps in occupied Germany following the Second World War
    - Sweden, 1945-1946. (Folder 4: 5)
      Materials pertaining to the situation of Latvian refugees after World War II, especially those subject to repatriation to the Soviet Union in 1945, and to protests concerning such relocation
  - Soviet Union--Politics and government, 1942-1943 (Folder 4: 6)
- Printed Matter, 1944-1948. (Box 4-8 and 10)
  Clippings, pamphlets, and serial issues, arranged alphabetically by physical form and therein by title
  - Clippings (Folder 4: 7-9)
  - Latvian serial issues. (Box 5)
    Most titles originating from Germany or Austria represent the publishing efforts of Latvian refugees in displaced person camps
    - Atbalss (Canada), no. 2, 1948 June 30 (Folder 5: 1)
    - Atbalss (Germany), 1948 January-June (Folder 5: 2)
    - Auseklis (Germany), no. 171, 1947 December 13 (Folder 5: 3)
    - Baltiešu Ziņas Austrija (Austria), nos. 95, 119, 120, 121, 122, 132, 134, 1947-1948 (Folder 5: 4)
    - Ceļs (Germany), no. 7/8, 1947 (Folder 5: 5)
    - Cī"ņa (Latvia), nos. 243, 253, 258, 279, 281, 290, 305, 1947; no. 4, 1948 (Folder 5: 6)
    - Dienas Zi"ņas (Germany), nos. 8 (incomplete), 44, 45, 72, 77, 84, 100, 101, 103, 1946; nos. 26, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31, 32, 1947 (Folder 5: 7)
    - Dzimtene (United States), 1940 October (Folder 5: 8)
    - Dzimtenes balss (Sweden), nos. 7-8, 1946; nos. 2-4, 6, 1947; nos. 2-3, 1948 (Folder 5: 9)
    - Gana balss (Sweden), nos. 1-5, 1945; nos. 4-7, 1946; nos. 1-7, 1947; nos. 1-2, 1948 (Folder 5: 10)
    - Ilustrētas Vārds (Germany), nos. 16-18, 1947; no. 26, 1948. (Folder 5: 11)
      Includes some articles in English
    - Jaunadze (Germany), nos. 68-72, 1947 (Folder 5: 12)
    - Labietis (Sweden), nos. 1-2, 1946 (Folder 5: 13)
    - Lapa (Germany), nos. 6-8, 1947 (Folder 5: 14)
    - Latgola (Germany), nos. 34, 37-40, 1947; nos. 57-59, 61-62, 75-77, 1948 (Box-folder 6: 1)
    - Latviešu studentu centrālās savienības biļetēns (Germany), no. 1, 1948 (Folder 6: 2)
    - Latviešu Ziņas (Germany), nos. 90, 93, 95-97, 1947; 1, 4, 9-10, 12-17, 43-44, 1948 (Folder 6: 3)
    - Latvija (Argentina), nos. 123-124, 1947 (Folder 6: 4)
    - Latvija (Camp Churchill, Germany), nos. 325-328, 335-336, 1947; nos. 337-340, 1948 (Folder 6: 5)
    - Latvija (Günzburg/Donau, Germany), no. 79, 1947; nos. 7, 10-14, 42-45, 1948 (Folder 6: 6)
    - Latvju Vārds (Sweden), nos. 13-21, 1948 (Folder 6: 7)
    - Latvju Zinas (Sweden), nos. 14-21, 46, 48-51, 1948., See also OVERSIZE MATERIALS (Folder 6: 8)
    - LCK Informācija Biļetens (Germany), no. 6, 1948 (Folder 6: 9)
    - Londonas Avīze (Great Britain), nos. 37, 40, 42, 1945; nos. 93-95, 110, 1948 (Folder 6: 10)
    - Londonas Latviešu Vestnesis (Great Britain), nos. 49-52, 68, 1948 (Folder 6: 11)
    - Meža Vēstis (Germany), nos. 8 and 12, 1948 (Folder 6: 12)
    - Pax Romana (Germany?), nos. 6-8, n.d. (Folder 6: 13)
    - Sauksme (Germany), nos. 1-4, 9/10, 1947 (Box-folder 7: 1)
    - Svētdienas Zi"ņas (Germany), nos. 56-60, 73-74, 1948 (Folder 7: 2)
    - Tāvu zemes calendars (Germany), 1948 (Folder 7: 3)
    - Tēvzeme (Germany), no. 80, 1947; nos. 6, 7-8, 10-11, 13-15, 18, 43-45, 1948 (Folder 7: 4)
    - Tiesībniks (Germany), nos. 1 and 3, 1947 (Folder 7: 5)
    - Valkas Ziņas (Germany), nos. 2-3, 6-17, 42-45, 1948 (Folder 7: 6)
    - Vēstnesis (Germany?), nos. 1-2, 1945 (Folder 7: 7)
    - Ziņas (Germany), nos. 156-167, 203-209, 1948 (Folder 7: 8)
  - Latvian miscellany. Fragments of bulletins, largely from DP camps in Germany, 1945-1948. (Folder 7: 9)
    Includes one newssheet from Sweden
  - Publications in languages other than Latvian (Box 8)
    - Balt-Press, no. 15, 1946 (Folder 8: 1)
    - Baltic Review, no. 1, v. 2, 1947 (Folder 8: 2)
    - The Beacon, 1947 October (Folder 8: 3)
    - Oras, Ants, Deportations in Estonia, n.d. (Folder 8: 4)
    - Im Ausland, nos. 2, 4, 22, 1948 (Folder 8: 5)
    - Izvestia, 1947 October 15 (Folder 8: 6)
    - K. Silinis: Paintings, Frankfurt am Main, 1947 (Folder 8: 7)
    - La Lettonie et les autres états baltes dans la politique internationale, 1946 August 10 (Folder 8: 8)
    - Lithuanian Bulletin, no. 12, 1947; nos.1/2, 1948 (Folder 8: 9)
    - Svensk Tidskrift, v. XXXIV, 1947 (Folder 8: 10)
    - Trud, 1947 December 4 (Folder 8: 11)
    - Vytis, 1948 March (Folder 8: 12)
- Oversize Materials, 1919-1947. (Box 9-10 and map case)
  Clipping, correspondence, diary, maps, photograph, and serial issues, arranged by size
  - Clipping and photograph relating to the sinking of Latvian cargo ships, 1942 February 2 (Folder 9: 1)
  - Serial issues, Latvju Ziņas (Sweden), nos. 1-65, 1945; nos. 1-99, 1946; nos. 1-100, 1947 (Folder 9: 2-4)
  - War diary kept by Kārlis Birkaivs during a military campaign in Kurzeme, Latvia, 1919. (Box-folder 10: 1)
    Includes letters and telegrams, relating to this diary, 1919-1947
  - Maps, drawn by Kārlis Birkaivs, showing telegraph lines used by the Latvian army in Kurzeme, 1919 (Folder 10: 2-3)
  - Four maps, drawn by Kārlis Birkaivs, showing telegraph lines used by the Latvian army in Kurzeme, 1919 (Map-case Map case)